Welcome to Executable Talk — a VS Code
extension that turns Markdown
presentations into interactive demos with
live code execution.
Executable Talk lets you open files
directly from your slides.
Let's open package.json to see the project
configuration.
And here's the README with the project
documentation.
You can highlight specific lines in a
file. Great for drawing attention to key
code.
Highlight a range of lines — lines one
through ten.
Or highlight a single line — line twenty.
Terminal commands run directly from your
slides. They require Workspace Trust.
Check the installed npm version.
List the files in the project directory.
Sequences let you chain multiple actions
together — open a file and highlight
specific lines in one click.
You can embed live file content directly
in your slides. This always shows the
current version of the file.
Command output rendering executes a
command and embeds the result right in the
slide. Useful for showing versions or
directory listings.
Diff rendering shows git changes inline.
You can compare any file against a
previous commit.
Any VS Code command can be triggered from
a slide.
Open the VS Code settings panel.
Toggle the sidebar visibility.
Search for markdown extensions in the
marketplace.
New in version 0.2 — YAML action blocks.
Instead of URL-encoded links, you can
write actions as readable YAML. Both
formats work side by side.
YAML blocks make complex actions much
easier to read. Here we highlight lines in
the extension entry point.
Sequences are dramatically cleaner in
YAML. This one opens a file, highlights
key lines, and runs a terminal command —
all in a single block.
Terminal and VS Code commands in YAML are
just as clean.
Run an echo command from YAML.
Toggle the sidebar with a single YAML
block.
Preflight validation catches errors before
you present. The validator checks for:
Missing files in your action links.
Out-of-range line numbers in highlight
actions.
Missing debug configurations.
Unavailable terminal commands on your
platform.
Trust issues when running in an untrusted
workspace.
These action blocks have intentional
errors. The validator will catch them.
This file doesn't exist — the validator
flags it.
These line numbers are way out of range.
When actions fail during a presentation,
you see a toast notification.
File open errors show which file couldn't
be found.
Highlight errors show which lines are out
of range.
Terminal errors show the failing command.
Sequence errors show a step-by-step
breakdown.
Toasts auto-dismiss after eight seconds.
Hover to pause the timer.
When editing deck files you get full IDE
support.
Autocomplete suggests action types and
parameters as you type.
Hover docs show descriptions and parameter
tables.
Real-time diagnostics show red squiggles
for errors.
Try it yourself — open this file and edit
an action block.
That's the end of the demo. Press Escape
to exit, or Ctrl+Z to undo any IDE changes
made during the presentation.